As many as 37 percent
of breast cancer cases may be
attributable to exposure
to bovine leukemia virus,
which I first did a
series about years ago.
In this two-part series,
I review the science
behind this phenomenon and update
it with the more recent data.
To see the original series, check
out the doctor’s note for this video.
"Bovine Leukemia Virus as
a Cause of Breast Cancer"
The incidence of breast cancer is
continuously increasing worldwide.
In the U.S., this amounted
to a 40 percent increase
in the incidence by the
turn of this century.
Currently, the main approach is
early detection and treatment.
That’s important, but why not pay
more attention to primary prevention;
in other words, protecting
people from being exposed to
risk factors for breast cancer
so that they never develop
breast cancer in the ﬁrst place.
“Overall, it is estimated that
20 percent of all human cancers
have an infectious origin.”
Viruses can trigger cancer
by turning on cancer genes
or turning off cancer
suppressing genes,
but they can also
contribute to tumor formation
just by causing chronic inflammation.
Currently, cancer-causing viruses
are considered the major
plausible hypothesis for a direct
cause of human breast cancer.
How did we get here?
It all started about 40 years ago
when a professor of virology
at UC Berkeley learned how mouse
mammary tumor virus was discovered.
Scientists swapped baby mouse pups
from mice with a high incidence
of mammary cancer with pups from
mouse strains with a low incidence
and found that the cancer
incidence matched the foster mothers,
showing it wasn’t genetic.
“It occurred to me,”
the professor thought,
“that humans are foster-
nursed on the cow.”
Bovine leukemia virus (BLV)
had just been identified as a
cancer-causing cow virus.
At the time only about 1 in 10
U.S. dairy cows were infected,
but now it’s closer to half.
We started out with
2/3s of herds affected.
Then, it was more like 80 percent,
based on their milk
testing positive for the virus, and 100
percent of the larger industrial farms.
And now, more than 9 out of 10
U.S. herds are affected,
a continuation of the
historical trend of the persistent
proliferation of BLV
within U.S. dairy herds.
We’ve long known that countries
with the highest milk consumption
also had the highest
breast cancer incidence.
And it’s not just a matchup
between dairy consumption
and breast cancer incidence
on the country level.
Individual women who are lactose
intolerant and consume less dairy
also seem to have decreased
risk of breast cancer.
Oh, but come on, there’s lots
of stuff in milk that could be
contributing to the cancer
risk like saturated fat and the
presence of cancer-promoting
growth hormones like IGF-1.
Yes, we know bovine leukemia virus
is present in marketed
beef and dairy products.
About half of milk and meat samples
turn up positive for the virus.
In fact, you can sample the virus
straight out of the air on dairy farms,
on surfaces, and in the milk itself.
Most milk is pasteurized,
but many dairy products
like raw aged cheeses are not.
And who hasn’t eaten a pink-
in-the-middle hamburger
at some point in their life?
Yes, we have evidence that
people are exposed to the virus.
Yes, we have evidence that people
are actively infected with the virus.
But it wasn’t until 2015 that we
learned infection rates were highest
in cancerous breast tissue, so much
so that as many as 37 percent
of breast cancer cases may
be attributable to exposure
to the bovine leukemia virus.
That was enough for me to
trigger a whole series of videos
on the role the virus
plays in breast cancer
and how the meat and dairy
industries responded to the news.
Okay, now that we’re all back up
to speed, what’s the latest update?
That’s what I’ll cover next.